Guide to the Kristin Bedford photographs, 1930s-2018 RL.10156
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Kristin Bedford photographs
1930s-2018
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bedford, Kristin
RL.10156
10 Linear Feet 15 boxes 172 photographic prints; approximately 75 related items
Kristin Bedford is a photographer based in Los Angeles. The 172 color photographs taken by Bedford from 2012 to 2018, derive from three projects: "Be Still: A Storefront Church in Durham," which consists of images of African American worshippers and their pastor in Durham, North Carolina; "The Perfect Picture," images from the multi-racial Peace Mission Movement religious community, founded by Father and Mother Divine in the 1930s, and the community's estate, Woodmont, near Philadelphia, Pennsylvania; and Bedford's latest work, "Cruise Night," a photographic essay on the lowrider community in Los Angeles, California. The "Perfect Picture" prints are accompanied by a variety of related materials (1930s-1990s), including movement publications and print ephemera, historical photographs, a CD of sermons, memorabilia, and other items; materials in this project speak to race relations in the 20th century, the civil rights movement, and African American religious culture. All three projects include a set of large color inkjet exhibit prints as well as a duplicate set of smaller handling prints, and an essay written by the photographer for each project. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Arrangement
Photographic prints in each series are in original order as assigned by the photographer.
Biographical Note
Located at the intersection of aesthetics and social realism, Kristin Bedford's photography explores race, visual stereotypes and communal self-expression. Through long-term engagement with communities, Bedford makes photographs that invite us to reconsider prevalent visual narratives around cultural and spiritual movements.
Bedford's work is held in private and public collections worldwide. Her photographs have appeared in group exhibitions in England, France, Spain and Malta, and in solo shows in the United States. Bedford holds a B.A. from George Washington University, an A.A. from The Fashion Institute of Technology and an M.F.A. from Duke University. Based in Los Angeles, Bedford works on photography projects across the U.S.
Access Restrictions
Access is partially restricted.
Original audiovisual materials are closed to use (CD-ROM in Perfect Picture series). Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies.
Please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use these materials.
Conditions Governing Access
Access partially restricted. Oversize exhibit prints in Perfect Picture and Be Still series are closed to general use due to their size; duplicate handling prints are available in each series.
Provenance
The Kristin Bedford photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2013 and 2019.
Collection Overview
The photographic work in the Kristin Bedford collection derives from three projects undertaken by Bedford from 2012 to 2018. The images explore three very different communities in the United States: two religious communities and their expressions of beliefs and faith, one in North Carolina and one in Pennsylvania, and the culture and identity of Mexican American lowriders in Los Angeles.
The project titled Be Still: A Storefront Church in Durham offers portraits of an African American community of worshippers of the Apostolic Deliverance Rebirth Outreach Ministries, in Durham, North Carolina. Images show the congregation as well as their church building.
The Perfect Picture project documents the daily lives of the remaining members of the International Peace Mission Movement, a multi-racial religious community founded by Father Divine in New York State in the 1930s, and was photographed at the community's estate, "Woodmont," near Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. The project title, "Perfect Picture," refers to Father Divine's use of photography as an analogy for creating a perfect life of faith and unity. The color inkjet photographs are accompanied by a variety of related materials (1930s-1990s): publications, photographs, some correspondence, a CD of sermons, memorabilia, and other items. The "Perfect Picture" project offers insights into race relations in the United States; African American religion; religious life in New York State and Pennsylvania; the 20th century civil rights movement; and the utopian philosophies of U.S. religious communities in the 20th century.
The Cruise Nights project, undertaken by Bedford in 2014, gives insights into the lowrider community of Los Angeles. The photographs are intense color close-ups of customized car exteriors and interiors, their drivers and passengers, and the lowriders cruising down expansive Los Angeles boulevards; the images emphasize not only the lowriders and their cars, but also the interplay of self-expression, gender, and photography.
All three projects include a set of large color inkjet exhibit prints as well as a duplicate set of smaller 11x17 or 13x19 inch handling prints for research use. A short essay for each project written by the photographer is included in each box of handling prints.
African American churches -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Photographs; African American churches -- Photographs; African American clergy -- Biography; African Americans -- Civil rights; African Americans -- Religion; Automobiles -- Social aspects; Churches -- North Carolina -- Photographs; Communal living -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Documentary Photography -- United States; Lowriders -- Social aspects -- California -- Los Angeles; Mexican Americans -- California -- Social life and customs; Photographers -- California -- Los Angeles; Religious communities -- New York (State); Religious communities -- Pennsylvania -- Photographs; Utopias -- United States -- Religious aspects; Durham (N.C.) -- Photographs; Los Angeles (Calif.) -- Photographs; North Carolina -- Religious life and customs; Pennsylvania -- Religious life and customs; United States -- Race relations; Color photographs; Digital prints; Ephemera; Inkjet prints; Optical disks; Peace Mission Movement; Mother Divine; Father Divine; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
- Be Still: A Storefront Church in Durham, 2012-2013; 1.5 Linear Feet 1.5 boxes; 1 oversize folder 60 photographic prints
  Scope and Contents
  This documentary body of work by photographer Kristin Bedford consists of 56 color inkjet photographic prints that portray African American worshippers and their pastor at the Apostolic Deliverance Rebirth Outreach Ministries, a storefront church in east Durham, North Carolina. The exterior and interiors of the building are featured in many of the images. Five of the photographs were taken as the congregation enjoyed a recreational swim at nearby Falls Lake.
  There are 28 exhibit prints in two sizes: 19 prints measuring 18 1/2 x 24 inches, and 9 prints measuring approximately 27 1/2 x 32 inches. There is also a set of 28 handling prints measuring 11 x 17 inches. An information folder is located in the box containing the smaller prints; it includes the photographer's statement from the "Be Still" exhibition at Duke University in 2013, and a printed list of thumbnail images, in color, with titles.
  - Handling prints, .5 Linear Feet 1 box 28 photographic prints 11 x 17 inches
    This box includes a folder with the artist's project statement.
    - Quadir, February 10, 2013 (Box 1, Image RL.10156-P-0001)
    - Apostle Hymond, March 31, 2013 (Box 1, Image RL.10156-P-0002)
    - Pastor Dubois, January 13, 2013 (Box 1, Image RL.10156-P-0003)
    - Jashua, November 4, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.10156-P-0004)
    - Larya, March 17, 2013 (Box 1, Image RL.10156-P-0005)
    - Nyema, February 24, 2013 (Box 1, Image RL.10156-P-0006)
    - Rahmel, March 31, 2013 (Box 1, Image RL.10156-P-0007)
    - India, August 12, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.10156-P-0008)
    - Denarius, August 26, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.10156-P-0009)
    - Anyla, March 17, 2013 (Box 1, Image RL.10156-P-0010)
    - Daquan, August 12, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.10156-P-0011)
    - Denarius, March 17, 2013 (Box 1, Image RL.10156-P-0012)
    - Divine anointing, January 27, 2013 (Box 1, Image RL.10156-P-0013)
    - Jashua, September 30, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.10156-P-0014)
    - Mother, April 7, 2013 (Box 1, Image RL.10156-P-0015)
    - Backroom, February 17, 2013 (Box 1, Image RL.10156-P-0016)
    - Cario, September 30, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.10156-P-0017)
    - Cario, September 30, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.10156-P-0018)
    - Denarius and Dantez, August 26, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.10156-P-0019)
    - Nyema with Drums, February 24, 2013 (Box 1, Image RL.10156-P-0020)
    - Pastor Dubois, September 9, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.10156-P-0021)
    - Pastor Dubois, September 23, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.10156-P-0022)
    - Man and Jashua, September 9, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.10156-P-0023)
    - Jashua, September 8, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.10156-P-0024)
    - Maya and Santonio, September 8, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.10156-P-0025)
    - Regina, September 8, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.10156-P-0026)
    - Maya, September 8, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.10156-P-0027)
    - Moe, September 8, 2012 (Box 1, Image RL.10156-P-0028)
  - Exhibit prints, 2.0 Linear Feet 1 box; 1 oversize folder 28 photographic prints
    Conditions Governing Access
    Oversize prints in this series are closed to general use; duplicate handling prints are available.
    - Color inkjet prints from the series "Be Still", .5 Linear Feet 19 photographic prints 18 1/2 x 24 inches (Box 2)
      RL.10156-P-0020 to RL.10156-P-0047
    - Oversize color inkjet exhibit prints, 9 photographs 1 oversize folder Approximately 27 1/2 x 36 inches (Oversize-folder 1)
      These very large exhibit prints are closed to general use unless with special permission of the ADA Curator; smaller handling prints are available for use in classrooms or the reading room.
      RL.10156-P-0048 to RL.10156-P-0056
- The Perfect Picture, 1930s-2014 and undated; 5 Linear Feet 10.5 boxes; 1 oversize folder Approximately 150 items
  This body of work by Kristin Bedford consists of 48 color inkjet photographic prints portraying male and female followers of Father and Mother Divine, founders of the multi-racial religious community called the International Peace Mission Movement. The images were taken at the community's estate, "Woodmont," in Gladwyn, a town near Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, during Bedford's five-week stay with the community in the summer of 2013, and depict the followers performing their many daily tasks and rituals, such as preparing meals, setting out the holy banquet table, gardening, and celebrating special holy days. Also featured in the photographs are interiors of rooms, objects such as reel-to-reel tapes of Father Divine's sermons, and the estate grounds.
  There are 24 exhibit prints: 9 prints measuring 18 1/2 x 24 inches, and 15 prints measuring approximately 27 1/2 x 32 inches. There is also a set of 24 handling prints measuring 11 x 17 inches. An information folder is located in the box containing the smaller reference prints; it contains the photographer's statement from the Perfect Picture exhibition, and a printed list of thumbnail images, in color, with titles.
  Accompanying Bedford's photographs are a variety of historical and contemporary items related to her project, including The New Day, the International Peace Mission Movement's serial publication; pamphlets and other print ephemera; historical photographs and correspondence (some photocopied); a CD of Father Divine's sermons; and memorabilia such as costume jewelry and a hat. Also included are two book-length works about Father and Mother Divine and the International Peace Mission Movement.
  Original audiovisual media (CD-ROM of sermons) are closed to use; access to file copies may be requested in advance.
  Please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use this collection.
  - Handling prints, .5 Linear Feet 1 box 24 photographic prints 11 x 17 inches
    - Father's Estate, "The Mountain of the House of the Lord", 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.10156-P-0057)
    - 15 Minutes Until the Banquet Bell is Rung, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.10156-P-0058)
    - The Perfect Picture, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.10156-P-0059)
    - Love Child with Father and Mother Divine, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.10156-P-0060)
    - Margritha After the Storm, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.10156-P-0061)
    - Miss Seraphim, Ready to Serve at the Holy Communion Banquet, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.10156-P-0062)
    - Miss Faithful Purity Truth, Watching for Visitors, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.10156-P-0063)
    - Listening to Father, Reel to Reel, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.10156-P-0064)
    - Mr. Nahum Sets the Table, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.10156-P-0065)
    - Mr. Victory In His Crusader Jacket, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.10156-P-0066)
    - Blue Guest Room, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.10156-P-0067)
    - Love Child and Miss Martha with Costume Jewelry for the Banquet (Box 3, Image RL.10156-P-0068)
    - Making Leek Quiche with Mother and Father Divine, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.10156-P-0069)
    - Sisters Bath House, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.10156-P-0070)
    - Miss Janet Kay, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.10156-P-0071)
    - Miss Life and Mother Divine, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.10156-P-0072)
    - Miss Life, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.10156-P-0073)
    - Mr. Victory and Mr. Mahaska, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.10156-P-0074)
    - Miss Life and Miss Truth, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.10156-P-0075)
    - Sunbeam Redeem, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.10156-P-0076)
    - Mr. Leon with Rose for Mother Divine, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.10156-P-0077)
    - Miss Seraphim's Ice Cream Cake, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.10156-P-0078)
    - Mother and Father Divine Ornaments for "American Christmas", 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.10156-P-0079)
    - Banquet China, 2013 (Box 3, Image RL.10156-P-0080)
  - Exhibit prints, 2.0 Linear Feet 1 box; 1 oversize folder
    - Color inkjet prints from the series "The Perfect Picture", .5 Linear Feet 9 photographic prints 18 x 24 1/2 inches (Box 2)
      RL.10156-P-0081 to RL.10156-P-0089
    - Oversize color inkjet exhibit prints, 15 photographs 1 oversize folder 15 prints approximately 27 1/2 x 36 inches (Oversize-folder 2)
      RL.10156-P-0090 to RL.10156-P-0104
  - Bound volume of pull-out sections of New Day, International Peace Mission Movement publication, 1974-1975; Stamped on front cover: "The word of God revealed: Father Divine's words from the Notebook of John Lamb."; 1 box (Box 4)
  - The New Day, magazine format, 1938 September-1943 January, 1996 April, 1999 September; 5 folders (Box 5)
  - The New Day, newpaper format, 1974 April-1986 April; 5 folders (Box 6)
  - The New Day, bound volumes, 1957, July-August; 2 volumes; 1 box (Box 7)
    Comprises a complete or nearly complete run of issues from July through August, 1957.
  - Other published materials, 1950s-1992 and undated; 14 items; 1 box (Box 8)
    Includes small volumes of published sermons and sayings of Father and Mother Divine, books, and numerous other small publications related to the International Peace Mission. There are two books on the International Peace Mission Movement and Father Divine, one published in 1954 by Sara Harrison, Father Divine: holy husband, and one from 1979 by Kenneth Burnham, God comes to America. There is also a volume written by Mother Divine on the history of Father Divine and the founding of his mission, published in 1992.
  - Additional project-related materials, 1936-2014; 19 folders (Box 9)
    Access Restrictions
    Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies.
    Folders house a variety of objects and papers related to the International Peace Mission Movement's history, Father and Mother Divine, and Kristin Bedford's photographic project. Includes but is not limited to: historical photographs of Father and Mother Divine, the International Peace Mission Movement's mansion (Woodmont), and followers (originals and photocopies); correspondence and papers (originals and photocopies); clippings (photocopies); tracts and pamphlets; ephemera such as postcards and stamps; hand-made decorative objects made of paper, fabric, and other materials; one CD-ROM of sermons delivered by Father Divine; and a list of questions for community members drawn up by producers working on a documentary film about the community.
  - Other Peace Mission artifacts, 20th century; 1 box (Box 10)
    Costume jewelry, watch, buttons, and other memorabilia given to Bedford as a gift during her stay with the Peace Mission community. The followers regard these objects as adornment that is worn for holy banquets and other celebrations of faith.
  - Red wool beret, 20th century (Box 11)
    Hat given as a gift to Bedford by the Peace Mission community.
  - Framed color photographs of Father and Mother Divine, approximately 1940s; 2 items; 1 box (Box 12)
    The photographs in their frames measure approximately 14x18 inches.
- Cruise Night, 2014-2018; 3.0 Linear Feet 3 boxes 68 photographic prints 13x19 (34) and 17x22 inches (34)
  Arrangement
  Arranged in sequence as assigned by photographer.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Pigmented inkjet prints on Epson Legacy baryta paper. Printed December 2019.
  These color photographs taken by Kristin Bedford from 2014 to 2018 form a visual essay on the culture of lowriders in Los Angeles. A few images were taken in Las Vegas, Nevada, and San Diego, California, where Los Angeles lowriders had visited. Image content includes highly modified car exteriors, vivid interiors, details such as decals and ornaments, and portraits of the women, men, and children who interact in this culture with the cars and with each other. The series comprises a set of 17x22 inch exhibition prints and a set of 34 13x19 handling prints.
  The artist, Kristin Bedford, offers this statement on her work:
  "Cruise Night is a glimpse at the beauty, grace and complexities of the car as a mobile canvas. It is an intimate, unstaged exploration of the female gaze and cultural politics in Los Angeles' lowrider car culture. Since 2014, I have spent four years immersed in the Mexican American lowrider community making these images."
  "The term 'lowrider' refers to both a customized car and its driver. While lowriding is an international phenomenon, it has a unique significance for Mexican Americans in Los Angeles as the customization of a car is intertwined with having a political and cultural voice..."
  "...Since its beginnings, the lowrider tradition provided a platform for young Mexican Americans, primarily male, to have a voice and be seen. Today there are tens of thousands of lowriders in Los Angeles. The movement is prolific, yet it maintains an element of invisibility in greater society. Lowriding is often pigeonholed by the art world as simplistic folk art and stereotyped by the media as crude and dangerous. I have seen a different reality – a sophisticated and beautiful tradition of self-expression that is passed down between generations."
  "It is not common that a woman creates a body of work around lowriding. Since the inception of the automobile, car culture of all kinds has been dominated by the male perspective. Making pictures as a woman in a space traditionally defined by men, and of a practice traditionally used to represent masculinity, places my work in tension with the prevailing depictions of lowriding."
  "With Cruise Night, I am offering an invitation to question all of these assumptions and stereotypes, and rethink the visual narrative around this often-overlooked American art form. It was an honor to be welcomed into the lowrider family and my hope is that these images begin to touch on the nuance, mystery and depth that I witnessed."
  A full statement by the artist and a paper inventory with thumbnails is available in the box of smaller handling prints.
  - Handling prints, 2014-2018; .5 Linear Feet 1 box 34 photographic prints 13 x 19 inches
    This set of handling prints are an exact duplicate set of the larger exhibit prints and are arranged in the same sequence.
    - Paula Sue, Kustom Oldies Harbor Area Car Club, Paramount, California, 2016 July 9 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0139)
    - Yahaira, Millenium Car Club, Los Angeles, California, 2015 December 27 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0140)
    - Gypsy Rose, Imperials Car Club, Hawaiian Gardens, California, 2015 July 12 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0141)
    - Imperials, Imperials Car Club, Hawaiian Gardens, California, 2015 July 12 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0142)
    - Kandy Lime, Klique Car Club, Chicano Park San Diego, California, 2017 April 22 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0143)
    - No Soy De Ti / I Don't Belong To You, Mary Saucedo, Vintage Ladies Car Club, Anaheim, California, 2018 June 22 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0144)
    - Anthony "Too Tall", Ordinary Life Car Club, Paramount, California, 2014 December 27 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0145)
    - Under the Sixth Street Bridge, Los Angeles, California, 2015 December 27 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0146)
    - Pachuco Manny, Whittier Boulevard, East Los Angeles, California, 2016 July 16 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0147)
    - Miss You Brother, Good Fellas Car Club, Whittier, California, 2015 August 15 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0148)
    - Tatuaje, Adam Jones Las Vegas, Nevada, 2015 October 11 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0149)
    - Raquel, Solo rider, Las Vegas, Nevada, 2015 October 11 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0150)
    - Samantha, At It Again Car Club, Elysian Park, Los Angeles, California, 2017 May 7 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0151)
    - Eddie "Penguin", East Side Bombs Car Club, Lincoln Heights, Los Angeles, California, 2017 May 4 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0152)
    - El Quetzal, Los Angeles Car Club, Hawaiian Gardens, California, 2018 July 18 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0153)
    - Lupita, High Class Car Club, Cypress Park, Los Angeles, California, 2015 June 13 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0154)
    - Purple Rain, Our Style Car Club, Los Angeles, California, 2018 July 22 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0155)
    - Whittier Boulevard, Heatwave Car Club, East Los Angeles, California, 2016 September 3 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0156)
    - Torres Empire, Torres Empire Super Show, Los Angeles, California, 2015 August 23 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0157)
    - Yvette, East Los Angeles Car Club, City of Industry, California, 2015 August 14 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0158)
    - Kandy Brandywine, Magenta & Violet, Good Times Car Club, Lincoln Heights, Los Angeles, California, 2018 July 22 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0159)
    - Impala Drive-In, Solo rider, City of Industry, California, 2015 August 14 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0160)
    - Ana, High Times Car Club, Boyle Heights, Los Angeles, California, 2018 September 9 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0161)
    - Cotton Candy, Good Times Car Club, Lincoln Heights, Los Angeles, California, 2018 July 22 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0162)
    - Pop N Son, Social Riderz Car Club, Paramount, California, 2014 December 27 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0163)
    - Don Julio, Emotions Car Club, Bellflower, California, 2017 November 26 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0164)
    - Blessing, Lincoln Heights, Los Angeles, California, 2017 March 19 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0165)
    - Stylistics, Stylistics Car Club, Bell Gardens, California, 2015 September 13 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0166)
    - Elysian Park, Elysian Park, Los Angeles, California, 2017 May 7 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0167)
    - Kandy Aztec Gold, Solo rider, Bell Gardens, California, 2015 September 13 (Box 13, Image RL.10156-P-0168)